Samuel Gompers Project on Microfilm 5632 mf A & B
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Samuel Gompers Project on Microfilm
1878-1937
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
University of Wisconsin
5632 mf A & B
16.6 cubic feet
149 microfilm reels
Microfilm, records (documents).
This collection is a combination of two collections: 5632 A - titled - American Federation of Labor Records: The Samuel Gompers Era, 1877-1937, consisting of 144 microfilm reels and 5632 B - titled - The American Federation of Labor and the Unions: National & International Union Records From The Samuel Gompers Era and this consists of 5 microfilm reels.
6091989
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, June 06, 2019
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, June 06, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Gompers (January 27, 1850-December 13, 1924) an English-born American cigar maker who became a labor union leader. In 1867 he married Sophia Julian. Gompers founded the American Federation of Labor (AFL), and served as the organization's president from 1886 to 1894 and from 1895 until he died in 1924.
He encouraged organization and collective bargaining to gain shorter hours and higher wages, the first steps, he believed, to emancipating labor. He also encouraged the AFL to take political action to "elect their friends" and "defeat their enemies".
The Gompers family immigrated to the United States in 1863, where they settled in the Manhattan's Lower East Side in New York City. His father started making cigars in their home and for the first couple of years Samuel helped him. Samuel started a debate team with some friends from school and that's where he gained his experience with public speaking and parliamentary procedures. Through his debating he also met a young man named Peter J. McGuire, who later became a big influence in the AFL.
Samuel Gompers was elected president of the Cigarmakers' International Union Local 144 in 1875. The union nearly fell apart in 1877 due to financial problems, which was not uncommon at this time in history. Gompers and Adolph Strasser rebuilt the Cigarmakers' Union with Local 144, by implementing a new high dues structure and programs to pay out-of-work benefits, sick benefits and death benefits to union members in good standing.
He was elected second vice-president of the Cigarmakers' International Union in 1886, and first vice-president in 1896. Despite the commitment of time and energy entailed by his place as head of the American Federation of Labor, Gompers remained first vice-president of the Cigarmakers until his death in December 1924.
Gompers helped found the Federation of Organized Trades and Labor Unions in 1881 as a coalition of like-minded unions. In 1886 it was reorganized into the American Federation of Labor, with Gompers as its president. He would remain president, with the exception of one year, 1895, up until he died.
His distinct brand of unionism led to the development of procedures for collective bargaining and contracts between labor and management which are still in use today.
Scope and Contents
This collection is a combination of two collections: 5632 A - titled - American Federation of Labor Records: The Samuel Gompers Era, 1877-1937, consisting of 144 microfilm reels and 5632 B - titled - The American Federation of Labor and the Unions: National & International Union Records From The Samuel Gompers Era and this consists of 5 microfilm reels.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4249: Nick Salvatore Research files /4280 P: ILR School Ives Hallway Portrait Gallery Photographs 5001 mf: American Association for Labor Legislation Records on Microfilm 5001 PAM: American Association for Labor Legislation Pamphlet File 5019: AFT Executive Council Transcript of Hearing of Local 5 5020: AFT Executive Council Transcript of Hearing of Local 537 5142: Glass Bottle Blower's Association of the United States and Canada Records 5216: Theresa Wolfson Papers 5262: Matthew Woll Papers 5277: Workers Education Bureau of America Records 5278: Utica Trades Assembly Records 5340: National Association of Manufactures Pamphlets 5360: Buck's Stove and Range Company vs. American Federation of Labor Court Records 5402 mf: Correspondence of American Federation of Labor President William Green on Microfilm 5417 mf: AFT Local 2 Scrapbook on Microfilm 5430 mf: Morris Hillquit Papers on Microfilm 5431 mf: Letterpress Copybooks of Samuel Gompers and William Green, Presidents on Microfilm 5471 mf: Max S. Hayes Papers on Microfilm 5488 B: BRAC Records 5502 mf: John Mitchell Papers on Microfilm 5503 mf a & b: Knights of Labor Papers on Microfilm 5541: Philip Taft Papers 5583/5: Archives Organization File (AOF) Part 5 5584: National Archives and Records Service Copies of Federal Documentation on Black Workers 5619: ACWA Records 5676: International Fur and Leather Workers Union Records 5688 mf: Binghamton Central Labor Union Records on Microfilm 5709 mf: National Women's Trade Union League of America Records on Microfilm 5718: Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners Documents 5751 mf: Papers of the President's Mediation Commission on Microfilm 5757 mf: American Federation of Labor Records, Part 1: Strikes and Agreement File on Microfilm 5760 mf: American Federation of Labor Records, Part 2 on Microfilm
Documents on microfilm -- Catalogs; Labor unions -- Officials and employees -- United States; Labor unions -- Officials and employees -- United States; Solidarity; Labor unions -- United States; Clarke, William P. (William Patrick), 1874-; Albert, Peter J.; Burke, John Patrick. 1884- 1966.; Cohn, Fannia M. (Fannia Mary), 1885-; Conway, H. J.; D'Alessandro, Domenico, 1867-1926.; Duffy, Frank, 1861-1955; Elliott, John T., 1836-1902; Evans, Evan Lewis, 1865-1955; Fischer, Henry, 1866-1908; Fitzgerald, Edward H., b. 1877; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Hillman, Sidney, 1887-1946; Huber, William D., 1852-1925; Hutcheson, William L. (William Levi), 1874-1953; Janiewski, Dolores E., 1948-, ed.; Miller, Harold L., 1949-; Rowe, Thomas W., 1868-1945; Schlesinger, Benjamin, 1876-1932; Schlossberg, Joseph, 1875-1971; Sigman, Morris, 1881-1931; Starr, Ellen Gates, 1859-1940; Tobin, Daniel Joseph, 1875-1955; Tobin, John F., 1855-1919; White, John P., 1870-1934; Zaritsky, Max, 1885-1959; Zuckerman, Max, 1868-1932; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; American Federation of Labor. Executive Council; American Federation of Labor. Mining Dept; American Federation of Labor; American Flint Glass Workers' Union; Boot and Shoe Workers' Union; Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America; Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express, and Station Employees; Federation of Organized Trades and Labor Unions of the United States and Canada; Federation of Organized Trades and Labor Unions of the United States and Canada. Legislative Committee; International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite, and Paper Mill Workers; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Stablemen, and Helpers of America; International Hod Carriers', Building, and Common Laborers' Union of America; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Seamen's Union of America; New York State Constitutional Convention. Industrial Relations Committee; Retail Clerks International Protective Association; Tobacco Workers International Union; United Cloth Hat and Cap Makers of North America; United Hebrew Trades; United States. Industrial Commission; University of Wisconsin
6091989
- Early Federation Records and the Papers of Gabriel Edmonston (Reel 1A)
- Executive Council Minutes. January 1893-November 1905. (Reel 2A)
- Executive Council Minutes. March 1906-January 1911 (Reel 3A)
- Executive Council Minutes. June 1911-February 1915. (Reel 4A)
- Executive Council Minutes. April 1915-December 1918. (Reel 5A)
- Executive Council Minutes. May 1919-August 1921. (Reel 6A)
- Executive Council Minutes. November 1921-December 1924. (Reel 7A)
- Vote Books. December 1892-August 1903. (Reel 8A)
- Vote Books. August 1903-December 1906. (Reel 9A)
- Vote Books. January 1907-July 1909. (Reel 10A)
- Vote Books. July 1909-August 1911. (Reel 11A)
- Vote Books. August 1911-February 1914. (Reel 12A)
- Vote Books. February 1914-March 1915. (Reel 13A)
- Vote Books. March 1915-May 1916. (Reel 14A)
- Vote Books. May 1916-April 1918. (Reel 15A)
- Vote Books. April 1918-July 1921 (Reel 16A)
- Vote Books. August 1921-May 1923. (Reel 17A)
- Vote Books. May 1923-December 1924. (Reel 18A)
- Correspondence and Files of the President. (Reel 19A)
- Letterbooks. Advisory Commission Council of National Defense, February-June 1917. (Reel 20A)
- Letterbooks. Advisory Commission, Council of National Defense, June-December 1917. (Reel 21A)
- Letterbooks.. Advisory Commission, Council of National Defense, December 1917-February 1920. (Reel 22A)
- Letterbooks. (Reel 23A)
- Letterbooks. Scrapbooks, 1886-1905. (Reel 24A)
- American Federation of Labor Convention Files. 1909, 1910, and 1911. (Reel 25A)
- American Federation of Labor Convention Files. 1911, 1912, and 1913. (Reel 26A)
- American Federation of Labor Convention Files. 1913, 1914, and 1915. (Reel 27A)
- American Federation of Labor Convention Files. 1915, 1916, and 1917. (Reel 28A)
- American Federation of Labor Convention Files. 1918 and 1919. (Reel 29A)
- American Federation of Labor Convention Files. 1919, 1920, and 1921. (Reel 30A)
- American Federation of Labor Convention Files. 1921 and 1922. (Reel 31A)
- American Federation of Labor Convention Files. 1922, 1923, and 1924. (Reel 32A)
- American Federation of Labor Convention Files. 1923, 1924, and 1925. (Reel 33A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 34A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 35A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 36A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 37A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 38A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 39A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 40A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 41A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 42A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 43A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 44A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 45A)
- American Federation of Labor National and International Union Files. (Reel 46A)
- American Federation of Labor Jurisdiction Files. (Reel 47A)
- American Federation of Labor Jurisdiction Files. (Reel 48A)
- American Federation of Labor Jurisdiction Files. (Reel 49A)
- American Federation of Labor Jurisdiction Files. (Reel 50A)
- American Federation of Labor Jurisdiction Files. (Reel 51A)
- American Federation of Labor Jurisdiction Files. (Reel 52A)
- American Federation of Labor Jurisdiction Files. (Reel 53A)
- American Federation of Labor Jurisdiction Files. (Reel 54A)
- American Federation of Labor Jurisdiction Files. (Reel 55A)
- American Federation of Labor Jurisdiction Files. (Reel 56A)
- American Federation of Labor Circular and Neostyle File, 1906-1937. (Reel 57A)
- Finding Aids. (Reel 58A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. April 1888-December 1904. (Reel 59A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. January 1905-March 1906. (Reel 60A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. April-August 24, 1906. (Reel 61A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. August 25-October 7, 1906. (Reel 62A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. October 8-October 27, 1906. (Reel 63A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. October 28, 1906-December 1907. (Reel 64A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. January-July 1, 1908. (Reel 65A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. July 2-August 29, 1908. (Reel 66A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. August 30-September 27, 1908. (Reel 67A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. September 28-October 16, 1908. (Reel 68A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. October 17-December 1908. (Reel 69A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. January-December 1909. (Reel 70A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. January-August 4, 1910. (Reel 71A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. August 5-October 1910. (Reel 72A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. November 1910-July 1911. (Reel 73A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. August 1911-April 3, 1912. (Reel 74A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. April 4, 1912-March 1913. (Reel 75A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. April 1913-March 1, 1914. (Reel 76A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. March 2-October 9, 1914. (Reel 77A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. October 10, 1914-April 1915. (Reel 78A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. May-December 1915. (Reel 79A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. January-June 1916. (Reel 80A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. July-December 1916. (Reel 81A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. January-March 1917. (Reel 82A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. April-May 18, 1917. (Reel 83A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. May 19-June 14, 1917. (Reel 84A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. June 15-July 12, 1917. (Reel 85A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. July 13-August 7, 1917. (Reel 86A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. August 8-September 1, 1917. (Reel 87A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. September 2-October 6, 1917. (Reel 88A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. October 7-November 8, 1917. (Reel 89A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. November 9-December 22, 1917. (Reel 90A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. December 24, 1917-January 25, 1918. (Reel 91A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. January 26-February 1918. (Reel 92A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. March 1918 (Reel 93A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. April 1-April 25, 1918. (Reel 94A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. April 26-May 1918. (Reel 95A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. June-July 1918. (Reel 96A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. August-September 8, 1918. (Reel 97A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. September 9-November 26, 1918. (Reel 98A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. November 27-December 1918. (Reel 99A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. January-March 1919. (Reel 100A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. April=September 2, 1919. (Reel 101A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. September 3-October 1919. (Reel 102A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. November 1919-May 3, 1920. (Reel 103A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. May 4, 1920-March 21, 1921. (Reel 104A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. March 22, 1921-January 20, 1922. (Reel 105A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. January 21-December 1922. (Reel 106A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. January 1923-May 1924. (Reel 107A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. June 1924-January 6, 1925. (Reel 108A)
- Files of the Office of the President - General Correspondence. January 7, 1925-February 1937. (Reel 109A)
- Speeches and Writings. 1894-1909. (Reel 110A)
- Speeches and Writings. 1910-1915. (Reel 111A)
- Speeches and Writings. 1916-1917. (Reel 112A)
- Speeches and Writings. January 1918-June 1919. (Reel 113A)
- Speeches and Writings. July 1919-May 1920. (Reel 114A)
- Speeches and Writings. June 1920-September 1921. (Reel 115A)
- Speeches and Writings. October 1921-April 17, 1922. (Reel 116A)
- Speeches and Writings. April 18-December 1922. (Reel 117A)
- Speeches and Writings. January 1923-June 1924. (Reel 118A)
- Speeches and Writings. July 1924-December 1925. Conferences. January 1901-April 2, 1917. (Reel 119A)
- Conferences. April 6, 1917-January 1920. (Reel 120A)
- Conferences. February 1920-December 1921. (Reel 121A)
- Conferences. January 1922-July 1923. (Reel 122A)
- Conferences. August 1923-March 1930. (Reel 123A)
- Hearings. February 1899-May 1908. (Reel 124A)
- Hearings. February 1910-April 1922. (Reel 125A)
- Hearings. May 1922-March 1924. Reference Material. 1878-1908. (Reel 126A)
- Reference Material. 1909-1916. (Reel 127A)
- Reference Material. January-November 1917. (Reel 128A)
- Reference Material. December 1917-March 1918. (Reel 129A)
- Reference Material. April-October 1918. (Reel 130A)
- Reference Material. November 1918-October 1919. (Reel 131A)
- Reference Material. November 1919-December 1920. (Reel 132A)
- Reference Material. January 1921-July 1924. (Reel 133A)
- Reference Material. October 1924-December 1925. (Reel 134A)
- Reference Material. 1926-1936. (Reel 135A)
- Appointment Records. 1902-1916. (Reel 136A)
- Appointment Records. 1917-1924. (Reel 137A)
- National and International Union Correspondence. (Reel 138A)
- National and International Union Correspondence. (Reel 139A)
- National and International Union Correspondence. (Reel 140A)
- National and International Union Correspondence. (Reel 141A)
- National and International Union Correspondence. (Reel 142A)
- National and International Union Correspondence. (Reel 143A)
- Mining Department Records, 1911-1915. (Reel 144A)
- Early Federation Records and the Papers of Gabriel Edmonston (Reel 1B)
- Executive Council Minutes. January 1893-November 1905. (Reel 2B)
- Executive Council Minutes. March 1906-January 1911 (Reel 3B)
- Executive Council Minutes. June 1911-February 1915. (Reel 4B)
- Executive Council Minutes. April 1915-December 1918. (Reel 5B)